A Guide to the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia General Business Records, 1795-1965
Library of Virginia
- John B. Danforth and Herbert A. Claiborne. "Historical Sketch of the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia, From its Organization in 1794 to 1879." (W.E. Jones, 1879) - Richard Love. "Founded Upon Benevolence: A Bicentennial History of the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia." (The Valentine: 1994
Of note are the vouchers and receipts of Alexander H. Rutherfoord. Included are accounts, agreements, contracts, drawings, estimates, receipts, and specifications for the Rutherfoord-Hobson House and Linden Row houses in Richmond, Virginia. The Rutherfoord-Hobson house was built in 1842-1843 by Alexander Rutherfoord, on land bought from his father, Thomas Rutherfoord. The house was located at 2 W. Franklin Street, Richmond. The Linden Row houses were built between 1847-1853 at 110-118 East Franklin Street, Richmond. The lots had originally been purchased by Thomas Rutherfoord, the father of Samuel and Alexander Rutherfoord, and later sold to his brother-in-law, Parson Blair. In 1847 Fleming James built a row of five houses which were called Linden Square, later becoming Linden Row. In 1853 Samuel and Alexander Rutherfoord acquired the lots and continued to build five more houses like the ones built in 1847. These papers relating to these historic houses are of special interest to researchers interested in Richmond architecture.
SERIES V: INSPECTION REPORTS (1944-1965)
The Inspection Reports series consists of 21 volumes of reports on houses mainly in Richmond, Virginia, 1944-1965. Included are a few reports from Danville, Norfolk, Petersburg, Suffolk, and Winchester, Virginia. The reports include the location of the house, corresponding Sanborn map volume number, use of building (house, apt., office, church), distance from fire hydrant, number of stories, construction material, type of heating, age of building, estimate cost to rebuild, and general questions about the condition of the housekeeping and location of the house. The reports conclude with questions regarding the risk of the house, whether the neighborhood was improving or declining, and whether the neighborhood would in the future be converted to boarding houses or shopping areas. Many reports include small sketches of the buildings on the back of the forms. It is unknown why certain houses were included and although the reports are arranged numerically, there is no other consistency with street or house numbers.
SERIES VI: COLLECTION LISTS AND TOWN AND COUNTRY QUOTAS (1796-1884)
The Collection lists, 1847-1884, consist of 26 volumes and is housed in 11 boxes. The lists are indexed by town name and also include the collector's name. Included are the name of the insured, policy number, and principal and interest collected for the year, often including information on previous 3-4 years of collection.
The Town and Country quotas consist of 56 volumes, 1796- 1869, housed in 37 boxes. The volumes begin with a recapitulation of the amount insured in each county or town and include the number of buildings insured, net amount of insurance, premium and quota for the year. The remainder of the volumes lists by county or town the declaration number, names of subscribers, names of transferrees, number of buildings insured, amount of insurance, premium and quota on each declaration, when the quota was paid, the amount of the quota paid, and remarks. Included are quota volumes for the country branches, 1796-1822, and town branches, 1796-1869. The volumes are indexed by town or city name.
Revaluations of insured property were required every seven years or whenever additions were made to a policy. Until 1819, the Society returned to policy holders the interest accumulated on its reserve fund in excess of the amount deemed necessary to pay annual claims for losses and damages. When costs exceeded income, the Society was authorized to require members to pay "quotas," the amount depending on the sum insured and the rate of hazard. Insured property was considered security and could be sold to obtain the quotas. Annual quotas were not required until 1809. From 1809 to 1846 the rate of the assessment was twenty per cent of the premium. In 1805 the Society decided to divide its business into two distinct divisions- town and country branches. This decision was made because it was thought that fires in towns were liable to destroy hundreds of houses, where fires in the country would only consume one house. Although administered by a single board and group of officers, the newly separated town and country branches had their own agents, policies, and treasuries. Income and expenses were divided into two accounts, and newly assessed quotas and payments for losses were based on the income generated by each division. By 1810 though the Society realized that it was more difficult to collect quotas from the cash strapped farmers in the country than the more steadily employed urban workers. In 1819 the Society stopped issuing policies on country properties and in 1821 it eliminated the country branch altogether. The Society now limited its coverage to structures located in Virginia's towns and cities.
Also included are two volumes, Record for Towns, 1805-1814, and Revaluation of Towns, 1805-1814. These volumes lists by towns the property insured, giving the policy and declaration number, subscriber's name, use of the building, insurance value, amount of premium, and if the property was burnt or if the policy was withdrawn or transferred. Both volumes contain full name indexes at the end of the volume.
Also included is a statement showing the value of certain houses in Fredericksburg, 1796 and 1822. The list shows who owned the buildings in 1796, the valuation and type of building and who owned the buildings in 1822, valuation, and the amount of increase or decrease in the property values.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series. Series have been designated for: I. Administrative Records; II. Correspondence, Incoming; III. Correspondence, Outgoing; IV: General Accounts; V. Inspection Reports; and VI. Town and Country Quotas.
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1795-1899 3.2 cubic feet (11 boxes); Boxes 1-11
  - Annual statements, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual statements, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual statements, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual statements, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual statements, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual statements, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual statements, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual statements, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual statements, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual statements, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual statements, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual statements, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual statements, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual statements, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual statements, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual statements, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Annual statements, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Annual statements, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual statements, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Annual statements, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Annual statements, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Annual statements, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annual statements, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual statements, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual statements, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Annual statements, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Annual statements, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - A Collection of the Acts of the Legislature of Virginia, In relation to the Mutual Assurance Society against Fire on Buildings in the State of Virginia, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, Rules and Regulations of the Mutual Assurance Society Against Fire on Buildings, of the State of Virginia, As Amended and Revised, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Historical Sketch of the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia, Richmond, VA., From its Organization in 1794 to 1879, compiled by John B. Danforth and Herbert A. Claiborne, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minute book, Vol. 1, 4 Jan 1796-28 Apr. 1802 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Board of Directors (Standing Committee) Misc. Reel 460b
  - Minute book, Vol. 2, 4 May 1802-16 Jan. 1805 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minute book, Vol. 3, 31 Jan. 1805-8 June 1808 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Proceedings, 31 Jan. 1805-5 Apr. 1806 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minute book, Vol. 4, 30 June 1808-3 July 1812 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minute book, Vol. 5, 14 July 1812-6 Aug. 1821 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minute book, Vol. 6, 29 Aug. 1821-22 Dec. 1829 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minute book, Vol. 7, 9 Feb. 1830-13 Dec. 1842 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Board of Directors (Standing Committee) Misc. Reel 460c
  - Minute book, Vol. 8, 3 Jan. 1843-28 July 1855 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minute book, Vol. 9, 11 Aug. 1855-30 Nov. 1869 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minute book, Vol. 10, 1 Feb. 1870-8 Nov. 1897 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Board of Directors (Standing Committee) Misc. Reel 2160
  - Resolutions, 1828-1829 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Board of Directors (Standing Committee)
  - Resolutions, 1865-1870 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minute book, Vol. 1, 17 Dec. 1795-30 July 1804 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Policy Holders (General Meetings) Misc. Reel 460a
  - Minute book, Vol. 2, 7 Jan. 1805-17 Feb. 1823 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minute book, Vol. 3, Nov. 1823-2 Dec. 1899 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Policy Holders (General Meetings) Misc. Reel 2160
- Series II: Correspondence, Incoming 1795-1865 23.4 cubic feet (40 boxes); Boxes 12-63
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent, then chronologically by year.
  - A, 1797, 1799-1802 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - A, 1803-1805 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - A, 1806-1809 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - A, 1810-1811 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - A, 1812-1814 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - A, 1815-1817 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - A, 1818-1820 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - A, 1821-1822 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - A, 1823-1825 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - A, 1826-1828 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - A, 1829-1835 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - A, 1836-1838 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - A, 1839-1846 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - A, 1847-1852 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - A, 1853-1857 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - A, 1858-1859 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - A, 1865 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - B, 1805-1810 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - B, 1812 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - B, 1815-1816 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - B, 1817-1818 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - B, 1819-1820 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - B, 1821 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - B, 1822 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - B, 1823-1824 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - B, 1826-1827 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - B, 1828-1829 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - B, 1830-1832 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - B, 1833-1835 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - B, 1836-1838 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - B, 1839 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - B, 1840 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - B, 1841 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - B, 1842 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - B, 1843 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - B, 1844 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - B, 1845-1846 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - B, 1847-1848 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - B, 1849-1850 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - B, 1851-1852 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - B, 1853-1854 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - B, 1855-1856 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - B, 1857 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - B, 1858-1859 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - C, 1795-1800 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - C, 1801-1803 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - C, 1804-1805 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - C, 1806-1808 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - C, 1809-1810 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - C, 1811-1812 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - C, 1813-1815 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - C, 1816-1819 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - C, 1820 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - C, 1821-1822 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - C, 1823-1824 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - C, 1825 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - C, 1826-1828 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - C, 1829-1830 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - C,, 1831-1832 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - C, 1833-1835 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - C, 1836-1838 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - C, 1838-1840 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - C, 1841-1844 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - C, 1845-1848 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - C, 1849-1850 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - C, 1851-1853 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - C, 1854-1856 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - C, 1857-1858 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - C, 1859 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - D, 1795-1787, 1801-1804 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - D, 1805-1808 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - D, 1809-1810 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - D, 1811-1813 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - D, 1814-1817 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - D, 1818-1819 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - D, 1820 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - D, 1821-1822 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - D, 1823-1824 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - D, 1825-1828 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - D, 1829-1835 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - D, 1836-1838 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - D, 1839-1841 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - D, 1842-1845 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - D, 1846-1847 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - D, 1848-1849 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - D, 1851-1853 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - D, 1854 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - D, 1855 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - D, 1856 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - D, 1857 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - D, 1858 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - D, 1859 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - D, 1860 (Box 24, Folder 2a)
  - D, 1861 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - D, 1862 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - D, 1863 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Da-De, 1865 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Do-Du, 1865 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - E, 1796-1807 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - E, 1808-1820 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - E, 1821-1834 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - E, 1836-1859 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - F, 1796-1804 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - F, 1807-1808 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - F, 1809-1817 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - F, 1818-1821 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - F, 1822-1823 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - F, 1824-1832 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - F, 1833-1841 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - F, 1842-1851 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - F, 1852-1859 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - G, 1795-1801 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - G, 1802-1810 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - G, 1811-1820 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - G, 1821-1823 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - G, 1824-1830 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - G, 1832-1837 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - G, 1838-1840 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - G, 1841-1845 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - G, 1846-1851 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - G, 1852-1855 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - G, 1856-1859 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - G, 1864 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - H, 1795-1798 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - H, 1799-1803 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - H, 1804-1807 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - H, 1808-1809 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - H, 1810 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - H, 1811 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - H, 1812 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - H, 1813-1815 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - H, 1816-1818 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - H, 1819-1820 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - H, 1821-1822 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - H, 1823 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - H, 1824 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - H, 1825 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - H, 1826-1827 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - H, 1828-1830 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - H, 1831-1834 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - H, 1835 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - H, 1836 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - H, 1839 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - H, 1840 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - H, 1842 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - H, 1843 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - H, 1845 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - H, 1846 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - H, 1847 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - H, 1848 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - H, 1849 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - H, 1850 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - H, 1851 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - H, 1852 (Box 33, Folder 3a)
  - H, 1853 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - H, 1854 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - H, 1855 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - H, 1856 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - H, 1857 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - H, 1858 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - H, 1859 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Ha-He, 1860 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Ho-Hu, 1860 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - H, 1861 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - H, 1862 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - H, 1865 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - I, 1796-1856 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - J, 1796-1804 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - J, 1805-1810 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - J, 1813-1816 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - J, 1817-1820 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - J, 1821-1826 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - J, 1827-1834 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - J, 1835-1846 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - J, 1847-1855 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - J, 1856-1859 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - K, 1797-1802 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - K, 1803-1805 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - K, 1806-1810 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - K, 1811-1834 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - K, 1837-1848 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - K, 1850-1859 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - L, 1797-1805 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - L, 1806-1815 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - L, 1816-1822 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - L, 1823-1832 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - L, 1833-1845 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - L, 1846-1848 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - L, 1849-1850 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - L, 1851-1853 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - L, 1854-1855 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - L, 1856-1857 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - L, 1858-1859 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - M, 1796-1800 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - M, 1801-1805 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - M, 1806-1808 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - M, 1809-1811 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - M, 1812-1815 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - M, 1816-1817 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - M, 1818-1820 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - M, 1821-1822 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - M, 1823-1824 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - M, 1825-1827 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - M, 1828-1832 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - M, 1833-1838 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - M, 1839 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - M, 1840 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - M, 1841-1842 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - M, 1843-1844 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - M, 1845-1846 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - M, 1847-1849 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - M, 1850-1852 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - M, 1853-1854 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - M, 1855 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - M, 1856-1857 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - M, 1858-1859 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - M, 1864-1865 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - N, 1795-1800 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - N, 1801-1807 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - N, 1808-1820 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - N, 1821-1826 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - N, 1828-1829 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - N, 1830-1831 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - N, 1832-1833 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - N, 1834-1835 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - N, 1836-1844 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - N, 1845-1849 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - N, 1850-1851 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - N, 1852-1859 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - O, 1795-1835 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - O, 1836-1859 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - P, 1796-1803 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - P, 1804-1808 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - P, 1809-1810 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - P, 1811-1812 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - P, 1813-1814 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - P, 1815-1816 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - P, 1817-1818 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - P, 1819-1820 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - P, 1823 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - P, 1824 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - P, 1825-1826 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - P, 1827-1828 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - P, 1829-1830 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - P, 1831-1835 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - P, 1836-1840 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - P, 1841-1846 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - P, 1847-1854 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - P, 1855-1859 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Q, 1808-1857 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - R, 1795-1799 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - R, 1800-1805 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - R, 1806-1812 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - R, 1813-1816 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - R, 1817 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - R, 1818-1822 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - R, 1823-1824 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - R, 1825-1826 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - R, 1827-1832 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - R, 1833-1838 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - R, 1839-1840 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - R, 1841-1842 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - R, 1843-1844 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - R, 1845-1849 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - R, 1850-1855 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - R, 1856-1859 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - R, 1865 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - S, 1796-1798 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - S, 1799-1800 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - S, 1801 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - S, 1802 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - S, 1803-1804 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - S, 1805-1807 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - S, 1808-1809 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - S, 1810-1811 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - S, 1815 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - S, 1818-1820 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - S, 1821-1822 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - S, 1823 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - S, 1824-1825 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - S, 1826-1827 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - S, 1828-1830 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - S, 1831-1832 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - S, 1833-1835 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - S, 1836-1837 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - S, 1837-1840 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - S, 1841-1842 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - S, 1843-1844 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - S, 1845 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - S, 1846-1847 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - S, 1848-1849 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - S, 1850-1851 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - S, 1852 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - S, 1853-1854 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - S, 1855-1856 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - S, 1857-1858 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - S, 1865 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - T, 1796, 1806 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - T, 1807 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - T, 1808 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - T, 1809 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - T, 1810 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - T, 1811 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - T, 1811 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - T, 1812 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - T, 1813 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - T, 1813 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - T, 1814 (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - T, 1814 (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - T, 1815 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - T, 1815 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - T, 1816 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - T, 1817 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - T, 1818 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - T, 1818 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - T, 1819 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - T, 1819 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - T, 1820 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - T, 1821 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - T, 1822 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - T, 1823 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - T, 1824 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - T, 1825 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - T, 1826 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - T, 1827 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - T, 1828 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - T, 1829-1830 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - T, 1831-1832 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - T, 1833-1834 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - T, 1835 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - T, 1836 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - T, 1837 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - T, 1838 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - T, 1839-1841 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - T, 1842-1845 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - T, 1846-1848 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - T, 1849-1855 (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - T, 1856-1859 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - T, 1860, 1865 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - U, 1820-1822 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - U, 1823-1825 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - U, 1826-1828, 1847 (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - V, 1796-1799 (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - V, 1801-1802 (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - V, 1803-1807 (Box 62, Folder 8)
  - V, 1816-1832 (Box 62, Folder 9)
  - V, 1833-1853 (Box 62, Folder 10)
  - V, 1854-1865 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - W, 1809-1810 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - W, 1818-1822 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - W, 1823-1824 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - W, 1825 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - W, 1828-1840 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - W, 1860, 1865 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Y, 1824 (Box 63, Folder 8)
- Series III: Correspondence, Outgoing 1805-1906 (bulk 1849-1899) 4.25 cubic feet (17 boxes); Boxes 64-80
  Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Letterbooks, 1805-1806 (Volume On shelf)
  - Letterbooks, 1849-1852 (Box 64)
  - Letterbooks, 1850-1853 (Box 64)
  - Letterbooks, 1853-1855 (Box 64)
  - Letterbooks, 1855-1857 (Box 65)
  - Letterbooks, 1857-1859 (Box 65)
  - Letterbooks, 1860-1866 (Box 66)
  - Letterbooks, 1866-1868 (Box 66)
  - Letterbooks, 1868-1870 (Box 67)
  - Letterbooks, 1870-1873 (Box 68)
  - Letterbooks, 1873-1875 (Box 69)
  - Letterbooks, John Blair, Collector, 1875-1881 (Box 70)
  - Letterbooks, 1879-1880 (Box 71)
  - Letterbooks, 1881-1883 (Box 72)
  - Letterbooks, John Blair, Collector, 1881-1892 (Box 72)
  - Letterbooks, 1883-1884 (Box 73)
  - Letterbooks, 1884-1886 (Box 74)
  - Letterbooks, 1886-1888 (Box 75)
  - Letterbooks, 1888-1890 (Box 76)
  - Letterbooks, 1890-1892 (Box 76)
  - Letterbooks, 1892-1894 (Box 77)
  - Letterbooks, 1894-1897 (Box 78)
  - Letterbooks, John Blair, Collector, 1893-1906 (Box 79)
  - Letterbooks, 1897-1899 (Box 80)
- Series IV: General Accounts, 1799-1913 (bulk 1799-1865) 12.15 cubic feet (27 boxes); Boxes 81-107
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Account books, 1873-1883 (Box 81)
  - Account books, 1883-1893 (Box 81)
  - Account books, 1897-1913 (Box 81)
  - Bank deposit books, 1850-1866 (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Bank deposit slips, 1819-1854 (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - Bank deposit slips, 1855 (Box 82, Folder 3)
  - Bank deposit slips, 1856 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Bank deposit books, 1857 (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Bank deposit books, 1858 (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - Bank deposit books, 1859 (Box 82, Folder 7)
  - Certificates of qualifications, 1850-1866 (Box 82, Folder 8)
  - Checkbooks, 1853-1859 (Box 83)
  - Checkbooks, 1859-1869 (Box 83)
  - Claims, 1796-1798 (Box 84, Folder 1)
    1796 McPherson, Hugh (Norfolk)
    1797 Legg, John (Fredericksburg)
    1797 Lock, Daniel (Loudoun Co.)
    1797 Magill, Archibald (Winchester)
    1798 Brown, James (Henrico Co.)
    1798 Dawe, James (Richmond)